Guide to the Mariposa Education and Research Foundation records, 1970-1987.
Mariposa Education and Research Foundation records,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mariposa Education and Research Foundation records, 1970-1987.
7300
Mariposa Education and Research Foundation.
7.6 cubic feet
Printed materials, office files, publications, 8mm film reels, audio reels, cassette tapes, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mariposa's organizational records, plus some of the ephemera and audio-visual materials it collected.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Mariposa Education and Research Foundation was founded to educate the public and its leaders about human sexuality and to bridge the gap between the accurate information known to researchers and the sexual beliefs held by most other Americans. For its libraries, it collected periodicals and other publications, personal files, legal documents, notes, manuscripts, clippings, and films pertaining to all aspects of human sexuality, and to the gay and lesbian experience in particular.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Mariposa's organizational records, including mailings and minutes of meetings. Also educational materials Mariposa created for the public, including posters and brochures, plus some of the ephemera (for example magazines and photographs) and audio-visual materials it collected. Themes include birth control, gay and lesbian rights and legal issues, S/M lifestyle, and other aspects of human sexuality.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Mariposa Education and Research Foundation.
Subjects:
Homosexuality.; Gay liberation movement.; Gay men.; Lesbianism.; Sex.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Collecting program: Human Sexuality.
Distinct sub-collections are cataloged separately. For a list of these component collections, search the Library catalog under the title Mariposa Education and Research Foundation records.
CONTAINER LIST
- E. Hugh Behymer (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Betty Berzon (Box 1, Folder 2)
- David Crandell (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Robert Dahlin (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Newton E. Deiter (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Martin Duberman (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Robert Hart (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Vance Henry (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Harry Langhorne (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gordon Martin (Box 1, Folder 10)
- David McWhirter, Andrew Mattison (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Larry Perron (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Robert Roth (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Richard Schlegel (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Larry Townsend (Box 1, Folder 15)
- C.A. Tripp (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
- Bruce Voeller (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Randy Wicker (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Perry Deane Young (Box 1, Folder 21)
- General Donor Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
- Donor Prospects (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Library Lists (Box 1, Folder 25-29)
- Board of Advisors (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Gay and Lesbian Archives (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
- Advocate (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Cataloging and Subject Terms (Box 1, Folder 34-36)
- Lesbian and Gay History Group of Toronto (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Publications (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Catalogs (Box 1, Folder 39)
- National Gay Archives (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Gay Health Centers (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Mariposa Publicity (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Audio-visual materials (Box 2)
  Two film reels: Close Feelings and Hope Is Not A Method; Audiocassettes: "Sol Gordon, 10/19/1973, Owego", "Getting Together is Life Itself", Blur "Girls & Boys" single; Mini educational films on birth control.
- Magazines kept by Mariposa (Box 3)
  Journal of Sex Education & Therapy, The Personnel and Guidance Journal, miscellaneous professional health magazines: The Female Patient, The International Journal of Psycho-Analysis, Society for Sex Therapy and Research Directory, etc.; miscellaneous mainstream magazines with GLBT related articles: Time, New York, Inquiry Magazine, etc. Most magazines from the 1970s and 80s.
- Photographs, photo prints, slides, 55 envelopes, 7 slide boxes (Box 4)
  Miscellaneous physique photos and other nude photos, including 7 Colt Studio black and white photographs.
- Mariposa brochure (Box 4)
- "You're Under Arrest", circa 1979 (Box 4)
- "What Has Jimmy Carter Done for Gays?", New York State Democratic Party, 1980 (Box 4)
- "A Teacher's Source Book" flyer (Box 4)
- "Coming Out!", R. Adam DeBaugh, 1980 (Box 4)
- Donahue transcript, 1980 (Box 4)
- "Drinking Patterns in Homosexual and Heterosexual Women", Lewis, 1982 (Box 4)
- Lambda Legal's "Living With AIDS", 1988 (Box 4)
- National Gay Archives and Library, Philadelphia, Barbara Gittings, circa 1980 (Box 4)
- Correspondence regarding sexual and gender identity disorders in DSM III, 1978-1983 (Box 4)
- Marital Satisfaction Inventory (Box 4)
- Mailings, flyers, brochures from gay/lesbian events, issues from Vermont to California, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
- Brochures, 1981 (Box 4)
- Mailings, flyers, circa 1981 (Box 4)
- Clippings, mailings, 1980-1985 (Box 4)
- Mailings, flyers, brochures, 1980-1991 (Box 4)
- Mailings regarding gay clubs, circa 1980-1990 (Box 4)
- New York City mailings, 1980s (Box 4)
- DS mailings (Box 4)
- Lexington, Kentucky (Box 4)
- Albuquerque, New Mexico-Common Bond, 1984 (Box 4)
- Washington State Network of Sexual Minorities, 1979 (Box 4)
- Oregon (Box 4)
- California (Box 4)
- "Primary Transsexualism", Milton Eber, 1982 (Box 4)
- Clippings-AIDS, 1984 (Box 4)
- Mailings, flyers, 1980-1986 (Box 4)
- San Diego Lesbian and Gay Community Center, 1974-1980 (Box 4)
- Newsletter, volume 1, 3 Zip disks (Box 4)
- Oversize posters (Mapcase-folder 1)
  Santa Barbara Gay and Lesbian Unity Week, May 23-31, featuring Bruce Voeller and The Mariposa Portraits; Homosexuality: the Last Debate, featuring Bruce Voeller; Grace Jones, New Years Eve 1983
- Audio-visual materials (Box 5)
  Miscellaneous adult movies, 8mm film reels
- Audio-visual materials (Box 6)
  Miscellaneous adult movies, 8mm film reels; Miscellaneous unlabeled audio rells, also audio reels labeled: Callahan Research Group Session, 5/8/73 and 5/21/73, Callahan Research News Session, 5/22/73
- Miscellaneous S/M ephemera, mailings (Box 7)
  Newsletters, club information, brochures, etc. Info. from TAIL (Total Ass Involvement League), FFA (Fall Festival Association aka Fist Fuckers of America), info. on fisting, An Exploratory Descriptive Study of a Self-Defined S/M Sample; also miscellaneous mailings to Bruce Voeller: Information from SAGE, MECLA, misc. democratic clubs; newspaper clippings.
- Mailings to Mariposa, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
- Fund for Human Dignity- memos, correspondence (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Porn and S/M mailings, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Mariposa bookkeeping (finances) (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Mariposa FC Appeal (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Financial statement, December 31, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Meeting minutes/Board correspondence (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Graphic Services (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Gifts in Kind (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Tax Returns, June 30, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Remittance Information, June 30, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Bank Reconciliations, June 30, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Extensions filed (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Audit (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Misc. financial materials (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Chart of accounts (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Non-cash entries (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Martin, Gordon (Box 8, Folder 22-24)
- Gays and Religion- NYC, St. Lukes (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Misc.- mailings, new clips, flyers, etc. (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Sexuality in Literature: Selected Readings on Human Sexuality in the 80's, published by Mariposa (Box 8, Folder 27)
- "Third Annual Freedom Banquet" booklet (Box 8, Folder 28)
- Springs Life newsletter (Box 8, Folder 29)
- Copy of Topoi: An International Review of Philosophy, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- National Association of Gay & Lesbian Democratic Clubs (Box 8, Folder 31)
- New York City PFLAG newsletter, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 32)
- People's Anti-war Mobilizer (Box 8, Folder 33)
- Donahue/Falwell interview transcript (Box 8, Folder 34)
- Untitled physique magazine (Box 8, Folder 35)
- A Gay Manifesto (Box 8, Folder 36)
- Postcard and Get-Well-Soon card (Box 8, Folder 37)
- Directory of Graduates: Rockefeller University, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 38)
- American Mercury, contains article entitled "Homosexuality in American Culture", August 1951 (Box 8, Folder 39)
- On Small Press as Class Struggle, by Merritt Clifton (Box 8, Folder 40)
- Wishing Well publication materials (Box 8, Folder 41)
- "Pirate Communities in the Seventeenth Century: A Case Study of Homosexual Society", by Martin Duberman (Box 8, Folder 42)
- Mariposa funding requests and legal matters, 1989-1993 (Box 8, Folder 43)
- Gay themed playbills (Box 8, Folder 44)
- Clippings (Box 8, Folder 45-46)
- Drawings by Sean: Calendar and datebook, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- The Gay Engagement Calendar, 1977-1979,1984 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- The Target Calendar, 1979,1982 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Colt Calendar, 1976-1980,1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Untitled physique calendar, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Fizeek Calendar, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- America the Beautiful- Blueboy Calendar, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- In Touch Calendar, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Mandate Calendar, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Stag Line Zodiac Calendar, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Hot Spots Engagement Calendar, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- A State of Man, Inc. Calendar, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- The Celebrity Calendar, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Club Baths International Calendar, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Sierra Domino Calendars/datebooks, 1976,1978 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Roy Dean's Calendar, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Annual Man Desk Calendar, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- The Gay Desk Calendar, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Man's Image Calendar, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Sierra Domino Ebony Iron Calendar, 1979 (Box 9)
- Hardbody Calendar, 1988 (Box 9)
- Copies of gay and AIDS related articles, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Clippings of lesbian/gay themed articles, 1980-1982 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- News clippings (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Copies of various articles (not news) (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Periodicals with lesbian/gay or AIDS/HIV related articles (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Black Women's Anti-Violence Project, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Book/bibliography lists, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Boycotts, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Casa de Cristo mailing, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Center for Women's Studies and Services, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Chicago Resource Center proposal request information, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Contact lists, Mariposa/NGLTF correspondence, misc., 1976? (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Correspondence: to Bruce Voeller re: spermicides and prevention of the HTLV-3 virus, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Correspondence: Letter and gift certificate from Dr. Kopecky, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Correspondence: Inquiry from a Mariposa donor, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Correspondence: National Coalition of Gay STD Services, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Ed Koch, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Entertainment (Box 10, Folder 18)
  Nightclub and party flyers, movie flyers, broadway play announcements, etc.
- Flyer for "Homosexuality: The Last Debate", Sen. John V. Briggs vs. Dr. Bruce Voeller, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Fund for Human Dignity materials, including financial statements and meeting minutes, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Gay-themed money making scheme mailer, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 21)
- Gay youth, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 22)
- Gay Youth Alliance San Diego, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 23)
- GGBC (Greater Gotham Business Council), 1984 (Box 10, Folder 24)
- GLID (Gay and Lesbian Independent Democrats), 1985 (Box 10, Folder 25)
- GSDBA (Greater San Diego Business Association), 1985 (Box 10, Folder 26)
- The Haworth Press: New Books & Journals in Human Sexuality, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 27)
- "Key Components of a Comprehensive AIDS Treatement and Research Program for California...", 1985 (Box 10, Folder 28)
- The Lesbian & Gay Community Services Center NY Garden Party Mailer (Box 10, Folder 29)
- Lambda Legal mailings, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 30)
- The Lazarus Project mailings, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 31)
- Letterhead (NGLTF) (Box 10, Folder 32)
- Los Angeles Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 33)
- Mariposa direct mailing to the GSDBA (Box 10, Folder 34)
- Mariposa library booklist (Box 10, Folder 35)
- Mariposa library mailing lists (?) (Box 10, Folder 36)
- Mariposa misc. (Box 10, Folder 37-38)
- Misc. flyers, mailings, etc. sent to Mariposa (Box 10, Folder 39-42)
- Materials from a file entitled "Movement Misc." (Box 10, Folder 43-44)
- National Republican Congressional Committe info., incl. "Upcoming Fundraisers" list, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 45)
- "Network" group announcements, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 46)
- "Newsletter Articles Ideas" (Box 10, Folder 47)
- New Ways Ministry mailing, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 48)
- Note from Alan(?) Brown to "David", re: interviewing gay fathers, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 49)
- NGRA (National Gay Rights Advocates), 1984 (Box 10, Folder 50)
- Parkside Lodge-Westgate (Chemical dependency and eating disorder treatment for gay/lesbian individuals) (Box 10, Folder 51)
- Politics (mailings) (Box 10, Folder 52)
- Research and paper: "The Civil Liberties of Homosexual Men and Women...", 1976 (Box 10, Folder 53)
- SAGE (Senior Action in a Gay Environment), 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 54)
- San Diego AIDS Project, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 55)
- San Diego Democratic Club mailing (Box 10, Folder 56)
- San Diego Gay Community Assistance Food Drive letter, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 57)
- San Diego Pride Guides, 1984, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 58)
- Venereal disease information (Box 10, Folder 59)
- Misc. periodicals with articles relating to gays, HIV/AIDS, pornography, etc.
  - Air Force Times. v.45 no.33, 1985: Mar. 4 (Box 11)
  - Army Times. v.45 no.30, 1985: Mar 4. (Box 11)
  - Berkshire Sampler. 1980: Nov.30 (Box 11)
  - Federal Times. v.21 no.2, 1985: Mar.4 (Box 11)
  - Free Press. v.15 no3 (Box 11)
  - Life. v.56 no.26, 1964:June 26 (Box 11)
  - Look. v.31 no.1 1967:Jan.10 (Box 11)
  - Navy Times. v.34 no.20, 1985: Mar. 4 (Box 11)
  - New York Times Book Review. 1981: July 5 (Box 11)
  - The Post. (Palm Beach) 1980: July 6 (Box 11)
  - Register Star. v.29 no.208, 1982:May 21 (Box 11)
  - This World: GAYS. 1981: July 5 (Box 11)
  - This World: Special AIDS Report. 1984: Jan.15 (Box 11)
  - UpFront. (Newspaper for Handicapped and Disabled Persons). v.1 no.1 (Box 11)
  - The Villager. v.48 no.46-47 (Box 11)
  - Weekly Soho News. v.7 no.3, v.8 no.8 (Box 11)
- Photographs and theater programs
  - Physique photographs, ca. 1940-1960 (Box 12)
  - Theater programs, ca. 1951-1981 (Box 13)
  - Theater programs, ca. 1951-1983; Includes handwritten notes on plays about gay men, and on gay men's reactions to various plays (Box 14)